<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Network on Sanjay&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/network/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Network on Sanjay&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.123.7</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>WebHook Tester</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/webhook-tester/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/webhook-tester/</guid>
      <description>What is a webhook?
A webhook is an HTTP POST request that is made when a change or event happens in a system. For example, this could occur when the system starts, stops, or when certain conditions are met. This HTTP POST request contains information regarding the change, which programmers can use to initiate actions.
Consider GitHub as an example. When a push event occurs (which is a webhook event), GitHub sends a POST request to the payload URL.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TCP</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/tcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/tcp/</guid>
      <description>TCP stands for Transmission Control Protocol. It&amp;rsquo;s built upon the IP layer and provides features like reliable packet transmission, flow control, congestion control, and congestion avoidance.
Why is TCP the most used protocol?
TCP is widely used because of the features it offers, such as reliable packet transmission, flow control, and others. Reliable transmission ensures data arrives complete and in order, making it crucial for applications like file transfers, email, and web browsing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>internet basics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/internet/</guid>
      <description>How information is sent across the internet? Internet is a network of networks, billions of computers interconnect make the internet, information is sent across the internet in the form of packets, packets can be thought of a little containers of data, if you want to share an image to your friend, first the large image is broken down into number of packets, and these packets are transferred to your friend’s computer, in your friends computer they are reordered and assembled together(not necessarily) to form the image</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
