<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Sanjay&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Sanjay&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.123.7</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>TCP</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/tcp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/tcp/</guid>
      <description>TCP stands for Transmission Control Protocol. It&amp;rsquo;s built upon the IP layer and provides features like reliable packet transmission, flow control, congestion control, and congestion avoidance.
Why is TCP the most used protocol?
TCP is widely used because of the features it offers, such as reliable packet transmission, flow control, and others. Reliable transmission ensures data arrives complete and in order, making it crucial for applications like file transfers, email, and web browsing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>internet basics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/internet/</guid>
      <description>How information is sent across the internet? Internet is a network of networks, billions of computers interconnect make the internet, information is sent across the internet in the form of packets, packets can be thought of a little containers of data, if you want to share an image to your friend, first the large image is broken down into number of packets, and these packets are transferred to your friend’s computer, in your friends computer they are reordered and assembled together(not necessarily) to form the image</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>event modeling</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/event-modelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/event-modelling/</guid>
      <description>event modelling What is event modeling?
Event modeling is a simple technique used to design a system. It generally takes relatively little time to learn and get started. In event modeling, we use sticky notes to write things down.
Sticky note colors and their purposes:
Orange sticky notes: Represent events. We write down the event occurrence in the past tense. Events are generally triggered by the UI or by some external API.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>learn go with tests</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/learn-go-with-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/learn-go-with-tests/</guid>
      <description>Part 1: Introduction This is an article about my experience completing &amp;ldquo;Go with Tests.&amp;rdquo; I wanted to learn a back-end programming language for web development, so after completing CS50, I first got started with web development from The Odin Project. However, I only did a few lessons and wasn&amp;rsquo;t very consistent. Additionally, I felt like every three out of five engineering college students were learning the MERN tech stack, so I wanted to do something different.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
